Finding Aid for Edith Gomberg Papers, 1940-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edith Gomberg papers
1940-2003
Gomberg, Edith.
0668 Aa 2
Edith S. Lisansky Gomberg was a professor and researcher in psychology and social work with special interest and expertise in the areas of alcohol problems and drug abuse in women. Gomberg's papers detail her active professional life as a researcher and professor with material on her research and teaching, publications, presentations, material documenting her various activities and involvement in her areas of interest, as well as correspondence and biographical information.
23.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by Judith Lisansky (donor no. 9661 ) in September 2005.
The Edith Gomberg papers are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Gomberg papers include restricted material in the following categories:
Patient/Client Records -- Boxes 7, 12-23
Edith Silverglied Lisansky Gomberg was a professor and researcher in psychology and social work with special interest and expertise in the areas of alcohol problems and drug abuse in women. She received her B.A. in Psychology at Brooklyn College in 1938, her Masters at Columbia University in 1940 and her Ph.D. at Yale in 1949. She has taught at several institutions including Yale, University of Puerto Rico and the University of Michigan.
She began her career at the University of Michigan in 1974 as a Professor in the School of Social Work. Since then, she held a number of different positions in various units of the University including a research scientist at the Institute of Gerontology, Faculty Associate at the Institute for Social Research, Associate Director of the Clinical Research Training in Alcoholism at the Alcohol Research Center, and Professor of Psychology in the Department of Psychiatry.
Her curriculum vitae (1999) cites "alcohol and drug studies," "gender and deviant behavior," "adaptation of the elderly: drugs, alcohol, gender differences," and "ethnicity and race issues," as her fields of interest and expertise. She is well-known and widely published and was often called upon for her expertise in the subject area. She was asked to speak often at many conferences, served on committees and boards, consulted on several research projects, and reviewed many publications.
Gomberg passed away on January 9, 2005 in Ann Arbor. Additional information on Edith's professional and personal life can be found on a website created by her family at http://www.edithgomberg.com
Th Edith Gomberg papers detail her active professional life as a researcher and professor with material on her research and teaching, publications, presentations, material documenting her various activities and involvement in her areas of interest, as well as correspondence and biographical information. Gomberg's papers contain the following series: Biographical, Activities/Involvement, Correspondence, Personnel, Presentations, Teaching material, Publications, Research, and Audiovisual Material.
Subjects:
Gomberg, Edith.; University of Michigan. School of Social Work.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Biographical
  The Biographical Series (0.25 linear ft.) contains a small amount of information on Gomberg including her curriculum vitae, abstracts and memorabilia.
  - Abstracts and key information on Gomberg (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia (Box 1)
  - Vita (Box 1)
- Activities/Involvement
  The Activities/Involvement series (0.75 linear ft., 1964-1999) can provide researchers an idea of Gomberg's involvement in the areas of alcohol and drug abuse in.
  - ALMACA meeting of committee on women, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Alumni working in substance abuse, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Conference on Alcohol and Aging, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Connecticut, Dept. of Mental Health, Alcoholism Division, Task Force on Alcohol and Addiction, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Chemical Dependency Policy study group, 1987 (Box 1)
  - National Academy of Sciences, Institute of Medicine, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
  - National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism
    - Alcohol Initiatives, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Alcohol Psychosocial Research Review Committee, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Extramural Scientific Advisory Board, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Planning committee, 1984 (Box 1)
  - National Institute on Drug Abuse, special review committee, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Nebraska Task Force on Women, Alcohol, and Drugs, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Research Society on Alcoholism, membership committee, 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Reviews, 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - Rutgers Center of Alcohol Studies, Advisory Board, 1993 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan
    - Alcohol Abuse Prevention Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Alcohol Research Center
      - Building Bridges Between Research and the Treatment Community, 1992 (Box 1)
      - Executive committee, 1988-1992 (Box 1)
  - Woman to Woman
    - National Advisory Committee, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - The Campus Generation, 1989 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (0.3 linear ft., 1958-1997) includes chronological as well as topical correspondence detailing Gomberg's professional as well as personal life.
  - 1958-1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1989-1997 (Box 2)
  - Alcohol and aging, 1976-1980 (Box 2)
  - Comision Sobre Alcoholismo, 1971-1974 (Box 2)
  - Knupfer, Genevieve, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Office of Substance Abuse Services, 1983-1988 (Box 2)
  - Pattison, E. Mansell, 1973-1977 (Box 2)
    (alcohol and women)
  - Requests, 1989-1993 (Box 2)
  - Rutgers, 1973-1984 (Box 2)
  - University of Puerto Rico, 1968-1972 (Box 2)
- Personnel
  The Presentations series (1.5 linear ft., 1959-1999) contains notes, outlines, drafts, and programs from Gomberg's many presentations to organizations, professional conferences, as well as seminars and workshops. The series has been arranged by organization and event. The finding aid details Gomberg's specific presentation topic for each event.
  - Annual review, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Appointments and salaries/money discussions, 1992-1997 (Box 2)
  - Emerita, 1998-1999 (Box 2)
  - Dept. of Psychiatry, 1990-1995 (Box 2)
  - School of Social Work
    - Faculty appointment, 1974-1986 (Box 2)
    - Tenure review request, 1979 (Box 2)
- Presentations
  - Miscellaneous and general (Box 2)
  - Brochures and programs (Box 2)
  - American College of Neuropsychopharmacology, Annual meeting, "Female problem drinkers: psychosocial perspectives,", 1993 (Box 2)
  - American Psychological Association
    - Symposium on current approaches to alcohol studies and to alcoholism, "Current clinical research in alcoholism,", 1959 (Box 2)
    - Annual convention
      - "Femininity issues in women's alcohol abuse,", 1984 (Box 2)
      - "Liberation and libations: improving research on women and alcohol,", 1986 (Box 2)
  - Association for Medical Education and Research in Substance Abuse (AMERSA) Conference
    - Betty Ford lecture, "Alcoholic women in treatment: new research,", 1989 (Box 2)
    - "African American and White alcoholic men in treatment,", 1995 (Box 2)
  - Betty Ford Center conference on alcoholism/chemical dependency, "integrating concerns in chemical dependency,", 1988 (Box 2)
  - Borgess Hospital Community Health Forum, 1974 (Box 2)
    (women and alcohol)
  - Canadian Foundation on Alcohol and Drug Dependencies, Keynote address, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Center for Forensic Psychiatry, "Alcohol and violence,", 1984 (Box 2)
  - Central States Institute of Addiction, "Women--current research issues,"1982 (Box 2)
  - Coalition on Addictions, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Columbus Hospital, workshop for women's chemical dependence program, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Federal Officials Association, "Alcoholism in industry,", 1974 (Box 2)
  - Frederick A. Coller Surgical Society, Spouse's program, "Issues of aging,", 1985 (Box 2)
  - Gerontological Society of America, "Treatment issues with special populations: women and minorities,", 1996 (Box 2)
  - Greater Toledo Association for Mental Health, "The female alcoholic,", 1972 (Box 2)
  - House of Representatives, Subcommittee on Human Services of the Select Committee on Aging. Educational forum on aging and alcoholism, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Illinois State Medical Society, "Women and alcohol: causes and treatment,", 1981 (Box 2)
  - Institute of Continuing Legal Education, "Managing the lawyer's life,", 1976 (Box 2)
  - Kent County Health Department, "Women and relapse," "Substance abuse and other compulsive behaviors,", 1992 (Box 2)
  - Kentucky School of Alcohol and other Drug Studies
    - "Current issues on women's use and abuse of alcohol,", 1977 (Box 2)
    - "Determinants and consequences of alcohol use and abuse: towards a biobehavioral perspective,", 1996 (Box 2)
  - Massachusetts General Hospital Seminar series, "Personality factors in alcoholism,", 1971 (Box 2)
  - McPherson Hospital, Keynote address, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Mercywood staff, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Michigan State University School of Social Work and Continuing Education Service, "An institute on alcoholism,", 1976 (Box 3)
  - National Council on Alcoholism
    - Annual conference
      - "Alcoholism and women: state of the knowledge today,", 1975 (Box 3)
      - "Women unite to combat alcoholism an interchange of ideas,", 1977 (Box 3)
      - "Special issues in the treatment of women alcoholics,", 1978 (Box 3)
    - Special topics seminar: "alcohol problems among youth and children of alcoholics,", 1981 (Box 3)
    - Wingspread conference on alcoholism and aging, 1981 (Box 3)
  - New Jersey Task Force on Women and Alcohol, "Women in transition,", 1980 (Box 3)
  - Northwestern Memorial Hospital Institute of Psychiatry, (women & alcohol), 1981 (Box 3)
  - Ohio Association for Alcoholism Programs, "Women alcoholics,", 1974 (Box 3)
  - O.U.R. House, Detroit, "Women and alcohol,", 1974 (Box 3)
  - City of Philadelphia's Coordinating Office for Drug and Alcohol Abuse Programs, "The woman next door: a symposium on women abusers of prescription drugs and alcohol,", 1980 (Box 3)
  - Research Society on Alcoholism, Annual Meeting
    - "Predicting age at onset for alcoholic women", 1988 (Box 3)
    - Various, 1989 (Box 3)
    - "Development and course of problem drinking and alcoholism in late adulthood", 1990 (Box 3)
    - 1991
      - "Comparing alcoholic women with positive vs. negative family history" (Box 3)
      - "Women and alcohol: research update" (Box 3)
    - 1992
      - "Comparing alcoholic women with positive and negative family history II" (Box 3)
      - "A comparison of black and white elderly men" (Box 3)
      - "Gender differences among elderly alcoholics" (Box 3)
    - 1993
      - "Elderly male alcoholics: who enters treatment?" (Box 3)
      - "Women and alcohol: related substance abuses" (Box 3)
  - Rutgers
    - Advanced School of Alcohol and Drug Studies, "Women, alcohol, and drugs,", 1986 (Box 3)
    - Continuing Education seminars in alcohol and drug studies, "Women and alcohol,", 1986 (Box 3)
    - International Symposium on Alcohol and Aggression, "Alcohol, women, and the expression of aggression,", 1992 (Box 3)
    - Summer School of Alcohol Studies, "Treating women alcoholics,", 1987 (Box 3)
  - Sheppard-Pratt Junior League, "Barriers to treatment and interventions,", 1990 (Box 3)
  - Silverman Conference, "Aging, alcohol use, gender and health status," [n.d.] (Box 3)
  - Soundings, "Rhythm and blues: women, roles and depression,", 1985 (Box 3)
  - South Carolina Commission on Aging, "Detection and early intervention in alcohol abuse among the elderly,", 1983 (Box 3)
  - St. James Cathedral Counseling Center, Professional Development Series, "Much wisdom, much grief: transitions of older adulthood,", 1999 (Box 3)
  - St. Paul's Episcopal Church, "Women and alcohol,", 1981 (Box 3)
  - St. Vincent Medical Center, "Overview: issues of alcohol use and abuse in the elderly population,", 1987 (Box 3)
  - United States Civil Service Commission, "Women and alcohol,", 1987 (Box 3)
  - United States. House of Representatives, Subcommittee on Health and the Environment, testimony, 1981 (Box 3)
  - United States Senate Subcommittee on Alcoholism and Drug Abuse, testimony, 1981 (Box 3)
  - University of Alaska, Center for Alcohol and Addiction studies, lecturer for summer school, 1979 (Box 3)
  - University of Illinois at Chicago, Women's issues related to alcohol abuse and violence, 1992 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan
    - Institute of Gerontology
      - "Drugs, alcohol, and the elderly: use/abuse/misuse,", 1979 (Box 3)
      - "Alcohol and older people,", 1981 (Box 3)
    - Peer education, "Alcohol and sex,", 1990 (Box 3)
    - School of Social Work
      - Fall Field Instructors' Day, "Alcoholism and the family,", 1975 (Box 3)
      - Program for continuing education in the human services, "Problem drinking--issues and interventions,", 1976 (Box 3)
      - Symposium, Current issues in psychopathology, 1977 (Box 3)
      - Symposium, Women and leadership in human service organizations, 1977 (Box 3)
  - University of Washington, School of Nursing Alcoholism Nursing Traineeship Program, "The woman alcoholic and the young problem drinker,"1973 (Box 3)
  - Veterans Administration Hospital, series on alcohol, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Washtenaw Juvenile Court in-service, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Wayne State University (problem drinking), 1979 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous presentations (Box 4)
    - "Towards a biopsychosocial perspective: psychological contributions" (Box 4)
    - Slides on various research projects and results (Box 4)
    - Women and alcohol, Outlines and notes (Box 4)
- Teaching Material
  Teaching Material (1 linear ft., 1961, 1975-1998) primarily includes teaching material while Gomberg was Professor in the School of Social Work from 1974 to 1990 and Adjunct Professor from 1993 to 1998. Teaching materials include syllabi, tests, as well as notes and outlines.
  - Outlines and notes, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Psychologists' seminar, summer school, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Social Work courses
    - SW500: Human differences, social relationships, well being and change through the life course, 1997 (Box 4)
    - SW508: The life cycle, 1975 (Box 4)
    - SW515/615: Drugs, society, and human behavior
      - Spring/summer, 1985 (Box 4)
      - 1986
        - Spring/summer (Box 4)
        - Fall (Box 4)
      - 1987
        - Winter (Box 4)
        - Fall (Box 4)
      - Fall, 1988 (Box 4)
      - 1989-1997
        - Winter-fall, 18 folders (Box 4)
      - Winter, 1998 (Box 4)
      - Class survey (Box 4)
      - Lecture material--outlines (Box 5)
    - SW518: American cultures
      - Winter, 1984 (Box 5)
      - Alcohol and the Jews (Box 5)
    - SW522: Basic social work research winter, 1998 (Box 5)
    - SW543: Substance abuse, 1983 (Box 5)
    - SW614/705: Psychological testing and social work practice
      - 1978-1983 (Box 5)
      - 1985-1987, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Lecture notes (Box 5)
    - SW614: Psychopathology, lecture notes (Box 5)
    - SW615: Alcohol and other drugs: core information and theory, 1983 (Box 5)
    - SW622: Interpersonal practice: alcohol problems, 1977 (Box 5)
    - SW636: Integrative seminar: substance abuse fall, 1985 (Box 5)
    - SW708: Issues in alcohol/drug abuse winter, 1982 (Box 5)
    - SW712, 1974-1976 (Box 5)
    - SW713: Alcohol usage and alcohol problems in American society, 1977 (Box 5)
    - SW724/728: Issues in the treatment of alcoholism
      - 1975-1976 (Box 5)
      - 1978-1980 (Box 5)
- Publications
  The Publications series (1.5 linear ft., 1948-2003) contains some of Gomberg's published materials as well as drafts and correspondence of publications.
  - Drafts and correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1987-2000; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Alcohol problems and aging, 1996-1997 (Box 5)
    - Black and white older male alcoholics: health and social consequences, 1994 (Box 5)
    - Drug abuse and the elderly, Hispanic-American paper, 1980 (Box 5)
    - Drugs, alcohol and the elderly, 1999-2000 (Box 5)
    - Ethnic minorities and the elderly, 2002; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - The etiology of alcoholism: the role of psychological predisposition, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Gender and disordered behavior: sex differences in psychopathology, reviews and responses, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
    - Gender issues in psychopathology, 1999 (Box 6)
    - The life course: alcohol use and problems, 1992-1997 (Box 6)
    - Sci-mat various articles), 1995-1996 (Box 6)
    - Substance abuse disorders, undated (Box 6)
    - Substance abuse in the elderly, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Women and alcohol book, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
    - The young male alcoholic--a pilot study, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
    - Various, 2001-2003 (Box 6)
  - Published
    - 1948-2003, 9 folders (Box 6)
    - Abstracts (Box 6)
- Research
  Gomberg's Research files (11 linear ft., 1940-2003) make up the bulk of materials in the collection. The research series documents Gomberg's various research interests, including various grants, ideas of projects, notes and outlines, as well as raw data, reviews of results, and preparation materials. Gomberg's early research, not necessarily alcohol and drug-related, conducted while at Columbia and Yale has also been included.
  The most detailed research files cover one of Gomberg's largest research projects on Alcoholism in Women studies. These studies on alcoholism in women began as a three year project from 1980 to 1983 and was then extended until 1985. This project included a detailed interview of over 1000 women on their personal background as well as their alcohol and substance abuse history. Materials include grant proposals, funding requests, data, and interview questionnaire drafts. Also included are 11 feet of the actual completed questionnaires (restricted for 100 years). Researchers may also want to consult Gomberg's teaching materials for her Social Work 705/614 course on psychological testing and social work practice, which overlapped with this study during a few years and may give some insight into the methodology of this particular research and interview process.
  - Early research (Box 7)
    - Alcoholism in women, Rorschach statistical analysis, 1958 (Box 7)
    - Epilepsy, 1947
      - Papers, 2 folders (Box 7)
        [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2047 ]
      - Raw data (Box 7)
      - Unused cases (Box 7)
    - Experimental design (Box 7)
    - Master's thesis, "The relation of intelligence to school withdrawal among negro boys,", 1940 (Box 7)
    - Research problems, 1943 (Box 7)
    - Removal of rewards and barrier-frustration in rats, 1945-1946
      - Experiments (Box 7)
      - Theory (Box 7)
      - Literature and letters (Box 7)
      - Experiments
        - Methods (Box 7)
        - Preliminary experiment (Box 7)
        - First runway experiment
          (October)
          - Data (Box 7)
          - Paper (Box 7)
        - Second runway experiment
          (November)
          - Data (Box 7)
          - Paper (Box 7)
      - Data, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Written material on thesis (Box 7)
      - Departmental seminar, 1945 (Box 7)
    - Rorschach
      - General material, undated (Box 7)
      - Training material and courses, undated (Box 7)
  - Later research
    - Research notes, miscellaneous and general (Box 8)
    - Adolescents (Box 8)
    - Advertising and prevention
      - General (Box 8)
      - Ads
        - Ethnics (Box 8)
        - "Secret sorrow of the suburbs" (Box 8)
        - Status ads (Box 8)
        - Young, active, sexy and woman (Box 8)
    - Alcohol and higher-order problem solving study, 1961; 1991
      - General (Box 8)
      - Follow-up (Box 8)
    - Alcohol and the elderly
      - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Questionnaires (Box 8)
      - Gender differences and lifetime abstainers (Box 8)
      - Lifetime abstinence vs. light drinkers (past) vs. heavy drinkers (past) / Reasons for quitting (Box 8)
      - Notes and outlines (Box 8)
      - Early vs. recent onset (Box 8)
    - Alcoholism-etiology and maintenance, 1988-1989 (Box 8)
    - Breast cancer research (Drawnowski), 1994 (Box 8)
    - A comparison of black and white elderly, 1992
      - General, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Paper: Black and white older male alcoholics: health and social consequences (Box 8)
    - Disease concept (Box 8)
    - Drugs other than alcohol (Box 8)
    - Ethnicity (Box 8)
    - Factors influencing treatment entry of elderly alcoholics, 1993
      - General (Box 8)
      - Sites (Box 8)
      - Subjects: MRC 2 (Box 8)
    - Gerontology (Box 8)
    - Gerontology/ethnics, 1990 (Box 8)
    - Grants (Box 9)
      - Adult women's health: a lifecourse perspective, 1998-2003 (Box 9)
      - Aging mental health: survivorship and gender, 1980-1982 (Box 9)
      - Alcoholism and the aged: central nervous system effects, 1987-1992 (Box 9)
      - Alcoholism in Black women, 1983-1985; 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Discus: "Health, use of leisure, and drinking choices among the elderly,", 1983-1984 (Box 9)
      - Elder abuse/neglect: role of alcohol problems, 1996 (Box 9)
      - Programs in serving elderly problem drinkers, 1979 (Box 9)
      - Skid row grant, 1966
        - Correspondence and general (Box 9)
        - "The chronic drunkenness offender in Connecticut" (Box 9)
        - "Proposed plan on alcoholism and drug addiction in Connecticut" (Box 9)
        - Research plan (Box 9)
        - Task force (Box 9)
    - Legalization (Box 9)
    - Marriages and sex (Box 9)
    - MAST study, 1977 (Box 9)
    - Michigan initiative for women's health, "Understanding women's health: the role of heavy drinking and health habits,", 1994 (Box 9)
    - National Survey of Black Americans, 1983 (Box 9)
    - Older women: patterns of retirement, 1977 (Box 10)
    - Psychological survivorship: a cooperative study of older women and men, 1977-1979
      - General (Box 10)
      - Papers, documents, 1979 (Box 10)
    - Questionnaires and surveys (blank) (Box 10)
    - Relapse (Box 10)
    - Stigma (Box 10)
    - Suicide (Box 10)
    - Suicide attempts (Box 10)
    - Treatment (Box 10)
    - Veterans Administration Hospital, Ann Arbor, 1979-1993 (Box 10)
    - Women and alcohol
      - Biology health liver (Box 10)
      - International perspectives (Box 10)
      - Wilsnack, Sharon (Box 10)
    - Work histories/records, data and drafts (Box 10)
  - Alcoholism in women studies
    - Alcohol-related health hazards of women, 1984-1985 (Box 10)
    - Alcoholism in women: psycho-social aspects
      - Original grant and continuations (Box 10)
      - Proposal supplement (Box 10)
      - Addendum to site visit (Box 10)
      - Funding (Box 10)
      - Year 1:, 1980-1981 (Box 10)
      - Year 2:, 1981-1982 (Box 10)
      - Year 3:, 1982-1983
        - General (Box 10)
        - Final report (Box 10)
        - Progress reports (Box 10)
          (years 1-3)
      - Year 4:, 1983-1984 (Box 10)
        (Rackham faculty grant)
      - Year 5:, 1984-1985 (Box 10)
        (ISR, NIH, OVPR)
      - Interviews/questionnaires
        - Earlier drafts, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Final questionnaire (Box 10)
        - Women's coping strategies questionnaire (Box 10)
        - Coping (Box 11)
        - Coping of daughters in alcoholic and nonalcoholic families, 1986-1987; 2 folders (Box 11)
        - Codebook (Box 11)
        - Code change book (Box 11)
        - Question by question (Box 11)
        - Respondent booklet (Box 11)
        - Summaries and tables (Box 11)
      - Methodology
        - Conceptual framework (Box 11)
        - Origin of items (Box 11)
        - Sites (Box 11)
      - Data
        - Age (Box 11)
        - AIW and AVTMH2 women reunited by popular will (Box 11)